Hey, you, behind me and to my right.
Ty za mną po prawej stronie.
You, wearing the gray coat.
Ty w szarym płaszczu.
I would like you to stop manhandling other people's bodies.
Przestań obmacywać innych.
A molester.
Molestuje ją.
I didn't!
To nie ja!
She's lying!
Ona kłamie!
Hey, take that back!
Odwołaj to!
Where's your proof that I laid hands on you?
Masz dowód, że cię dotknąłem?
Hey, are you listening to me?
Słyszysz ty mnie?
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
FEAST
UCZTA
Looks like they've chosen the winner of the Kayama Fantasy Literature Award.
Wybrano zwycięzcę nagrody literackiej Kayamy.
The Seventh Transformation, by Yoshimi Dai, right?
Yoshimi Dai, Siódma transformacja, tak?
Oh, you've read it?
Czytałeś ją?
It's about a guy who gained the ability to talk to reptiles.
Jest o chłopaku, który potrafi rozmawiać z gadami.
It's totally implausible.
Totalna fikcja.
Not again.
Tylko nie to.
This makes 84.
Już 84.
Mincemeat Murders?
Morderstwa zmielonego mięsa? Już mnie to nie dziwi.
Thanks for breakfast.
Dziękuję.
Oh, you didn't even eat half.
Nie zjadłeś nawet połowy.
Yeah.
No nie.
I may be the only person in the whole world
Chyba jestem jedyną osobą na świecie,
who knows the truth behind those murders.
która wie, kto stoi za tymi morderstwami.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
Morning.
Cześć.
You know, you've changed recently.
Zmieniłeś się.
Huh? Me?
Co? Ja?
Yeah.
Tak.
I don't think so.
To nieprawda.
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
I know I just heard a voice.
Słyszałem jakiś głos.
Right here.
Tutaj.
Migi?
Migi?
I was just thinking something tickled.
Czułem łaskotanie.
What's wrong?
Coś się stało?
Oh, nothing.
Nie, nic.
One of my kind is near.
Zbliża się jeden z moich.
Again?
Znowu?
It's slowly coming closer.
Idzie tu powoli.
But there haven't been any Mincemeat Murders around here.
Ale tutaj nie było żadnego morderstwa.
It's possible they just haven't found any bodies yet.
Może jeszcze nie odnaleziono ciał.
It's about 70 meters away from us.
Jest 70 metrów przed nami.
Sixty meters.
Sześćdziesiąt.
Don't tell me.
Nie mów, że…
It's inside this building.
Jest w budynku.
Inside here.
Jest tutaj.
Where is it?
Gdzie jest?
Who is it?
Kim jest?
A guy?
To chłopak?
A girl?
Czy dziewczyna?
Approximately 30 meters away.
Jest 30 metrów od nas.
I am certain it's someone in here.
Na pewno tutaj jest.
Thirty meters?
Trzydzieści metrów?
Don't make eye contact.
Nie patrz mu w oczy, bo cię znajdzie.
It's looking for us, too,
Też nas szuka,
but thanks to the crowd, it seems unable to locate us.
ale w tłumie nie może nas zlokalizować.
Good morning, everyone.
Dzień dobry.
I'd like to introduce the new math teacher who'll be subbing in
Przedstawiam nową nauczycielkę matematyki,
for Matsuyama-sensei, who's been hospitalized after a traffic accident.
która zastąpi pana Matsuyamę, który leży w szpitalu po wypadku.
Come on up, Tamiya-sensei.
Zapraszam, Tamiya-sensei.
My name is Tamiya Ryoko.
Nazywam się Tamiya Ryoko.
It's nice to meet you all.
Miło was poznać.
-It's her. -What?
- To ona. - Co?
In addition, Yamamoto-sensei will become the new homeroom teacher
Poza tym pan Yamamoto zostanie nowym wychowawcą klasy 3-3…
Class 3-3?
Klasy 3-3?
That's her class.
To jej klasa.
…and Tamiya-sensei will be the assistant homeroom teacher.
…a pani Tamiya będzie jego zastępczynią.
Don't look, Shinichi!
Nie patrz na nią!
She's looking at me.
Spojrzała na mnie.
She's quite the looker.
Piękna kobieta.
Yeah.
Tak.
She found me.
Znalazła mnie.
Listen up.
Słuchajcie.
After doing five laps around the field, stretch again to loosen up your muscles.
Przebiegnijcie pięć okrążeń i się rozciągnijcie.
Then we'll split into two groups and play a match.
Potem podzielimy się na dwie grupy i zagramy mecz.
-I hope you've all read up on the rules. -What a surprise.
- Znacie zasady? - A to niespodzianka.
-They might be on the next exam. -Even after taking over the head,
Przejęła mózg
she managed to retain and maintain the host's specific position in society.
i udało jej się utrzymać status społeczny gospodarza.
Not to mention, she's teaching humans.
A do tego będzie uczyć ludzi.
She is very gifted.
Ma talent.
Why are you putting her on a pedestal?
Dlaczego ją tak wychwalasz?
We have to do something.
Musimy coś zrobić.
What do you mean by that?
To znaczy?
Well, don't we?
A nie?
She's going to eat everyone.
Wszystkich zje.
No, that's unlikely.
Wątpię.
She desires to blend into human society.
Chce być częścią społeczeństwa.
She will not use humans in her immediate social circles as food.
Nie będzie się żywić ludźmi ze swojego otoczenia.
They should be safe.
Są bezpieczni.
How are you so sure?
Skąd ta pewność?
Well, let's just monitor the situation for now.
Obserwujmy ją.
How can Migi sleep at a time like this?
Jak Migi może spać w takiej chwili?
Right now, if she were to…
Wygląda, jakby chciała…
All right, use this formula
Użyjcie tego wzoru
to solve problems six through 12.
do rozwiązania zadań od szóstego do 12.
-Izumi-kun. -She's here!
- Izumi-kun. - Jest tu!
What's wrong?
Co się dzieje?
You don't seem to be making any progress.
Nic nie napisałeś.
Oh… Well…
No ja…
Sorry.
Przepraszam.
Bow!
Ukłon!
Izumi-kun, come to the guidance office later, would you?
Izumi-kun, przyjdź później go gabinetu pedagogicznego.
All right?
Dobrze?
-Hey, did you do something? -No.
- Przeskrobałeś coś? - Nie.
I'm jealous!
Ale ci zazdroszczę!
I'd love to get a personal lesson from a babe like her.
Poszedłbym na korki do takiej ślicznotki.
Hey, there's a babe right here.
Ślicznotka to jest tutaj.
Right, Izumi-kun?
Prawda, Izumi-kun?
Nah, you've got nothing on Tamiya-sensei's mature beauty.
Nie możesz się równać z dojrzałym pięknem pani Tamiyi.
But I guess she prefers guys like Izumi.
Ale ona chyba woli takich chłopaków jak Izumi.
Who'd have thought.
Kto by pomyślał?
What are you talking about?
Co ty wygadujesz? Nie masz o niczym pojęcia!
You're the one without a clue.
To ty nie masz pojęcia.
Shinichi.
Shinichi.
She's approximately ten meters away.
Jest dziesięć metrów przed nami.
You're awake now?
Nie śpisz?
GUIDANCE OFFICE
GABINET PEDAGOGICZNY
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Come in, please.
Wejdź.
Izumi Shinichi-kun, I believe you know what I am.
Izumi Shinichi-kun, wiesz, czym jestem.
Yeah.
No wiem.
"Yeah"?
„No wiem”?
That's no way to speak to your teacher, is it?
Nie mówimy tak do nauczycieli.
There's no need to be so tense.
Nie denerwuj się tak.
Your right hand should know that I have no intention of killing you.
Twoja prawa ręka powinna wiedzieć, że nie chcę cię zabić.
Besides, if we were to fight in such close quarters,
Poza tym walka w takim ciasnym pomieszczeniu
we would both end up mortally wounded.
zabiłaby nas oboje.
I would like to talk some more with you.
Chcę z tobą porozmawiać.
Can you make time to meet after school today?
Możemy się spotkać po szkole?
All right.
Dobrze.
What if it's a trap?
A jeśli to pułapka?
I want nothing to do with this!
Nie mieszajcie mnie w to!
Why are humans so irrational?
Dlaczego ludzie są tacy irracjonalni?
What?
Co?
If I wanted to kill you, I already would have.
Gdybym chciała, już bym cię zabiła.
I am curious about you.
Zainteresowałeś mnie.
You are the first case of this nature I have come across.
Jesteś pierwszym takim przypadkiem.
That's why I want more data.
Muszę zebrać więcej danych.
I'd like to exchange information
Chcę się wymienić informacjami
and discuss the future with you.
i omówić z tobą przyszłość.
The future?
Przyszłość?
Well, that's all I wanted to say.
To ci chciałam powiedzieć.
Tamiya-sensei.
Tamiya-sensei.
Yes?
Tak?
Do you have any plans today?
Ma pani dzisiaj jakieś plany?
Yes, I am counseling some students.
Tak, mam korepetycje z uczniami.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Hey, come with me to the bookstore.
Chodź ze mną do księgarni.
Sure.
Dobrze.
Hey, that's…
Hej, to…
Shinichi, roll up your sleeves.
Shinichi, podciągnij rękawy.
Why?
Po co?
It's not like we're going to fight.
Nie będziemy się bić.
-Because there are two people coming. -Huh?
Idą dwie osoby.
Or should I say, two of my kind?
Są z mojego gatunku.
So it was a trap?
Czyli to pułapka?
We don't know that yet.
Jeszcze nie wiemy.
More importantly, Shinichi,
A co najważniejsze,
slow down your heartbeat some, will you?
obniż sobie tętno.
You're making me anxious.
Przez ciebie się stresuję.
Easy for you to say!
Łatwo ci mówić!
Sorry for the wait.
Przepraszam za spóźnienie.
Allow me to introduce you to A-san.
Przedstawiam ci pana X.
"A-san"?
„Pana X”?
He doesn't have a name.
Nie ma imienia.
Who the hell is he?
Kto to, do cholery?
How can we consider him one of us?
Jak możemy go uważać za jednego z nas?
Stop it.
Przestań.
There is no advantage in trying to kill each other here.
Nie ma sensu się tutaj zabijać.
I see.
Rozumiem.
So you have only met those two types so far.
Czyli spotkałeś tylko to te dwa osobniki.
Yeah.
Tak.
So, Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
What do you think we are?
Jak myślisz, czym jesteśmy?
Man-eating monsters.
Potworami jedzącymi ludzi.
What else should I think?
A czym innym?
Well, you see, A-san and I tried having sex.
Pan X i ja próbowaliśmy uprawiać seks.
Sorry!
Przepraszam!
Excuse me!
Proszę mi wybaczyć!
What do you think happened as a result?
Jak myślisz, co się stało?
Yes. I became pregnant.
Tak. Zaszłam w ciążę.
So, here's a question for you.
Więc mam do ciebie pytanie.
The "thing" that's growing inside me now, what do you think it is?
Jak myślisz, czym jest to „coś”, co we mnie rośnie?
Well…
No cóż…
A normal human being, no?
To normalny człowiek, prawda?
Well done.
Zgadza się.
Yes, an ordinary human baby.
Tak, to normalne dziecko.
Then, what does that make us?
Więc czym jesteśmy?
I don't know.
Nie wiem.
That's what I'd like to ask, too.
Sam chciałbym o to zapytać.
You eat other humans in order to keep your human host alive.
Zjadacie innych ludzi, żeby wasz gospodarz nie umarł.
That's like cannibalism.
To kanibalizm.
Why would you do something like that?
Dlaczego to robicie?
Did you try asking that to your right hand?
Pytałeś o to swoją prawą rękę?
I receive nutrients directly through Shinichi's blood.
Pobieram substancje odżywcze z krwi Shinichiego.
I consequently do not experience hunger
Nie czuję głodu i nie wiem, dlaczego miałbym być kanibalem.
We have no reproductive capabilities
Nie potrafimy się rozmnażać
and endlessly engage in quasi-cannibalistic activities.
i angażujemy się w kanibalistyczne aktywności.
Do such life forms exist anywhere else?
Takie istoty żyją gdziekolwiek indziej?
I thought that strange as well.
Dla mnie też jest to dziwne.
Do you count as a life form or not?
Jesteście formą życia czy nie?
Either way,
I tak trudno mi uwierzyć, że jesteście z tego świata.
I'm leaving.
Wychodzę.
Knowing what I am will not change anything.
To, że będę wiedział, czym jestem, niczego nie zmieni.
I will eat when I feel hungry
Będę jadł, gdy będę głodny, i usunę tych, którzy staną mi na drodze.
That's all there is.
I tyle.
He is dangerous.
Jest niebezpieczny.
He should be eliminated.
Trzeba go usunąć.
Perhaps it's a difference in our maturation environments.
Dojrzewaliśmy w innym środowisku.
So…
Więc…
Humans can take illogical actions at times,
Ludzie czasami zachowują się nielogicznie,
so I feel I should give you a warning.
więc muszę cię ostrzec.
Supposing you choose to see me as an enemy and cause a scene,
Jeśli uznasz mnie za wroga i zrobisz aferę,
you are at a greater disadvantage since you cannot change your face.
będziesz w gorszej sytuacji, bo nie możesz zmieniać twarzy.
I prefer to safeguard my current "human" identity as well,
Ja też chcę chronić swoją obecną tożsamość,
so I do not intend to do anything extreme.
więc nie zrobię nic radykalnego.
However, if I so choose, I can take on an entire classroom…
Ale jeśli będę chciała, mogę walczyć z całą klasą…
and massacre everyone in three seconds.
i zabić wszystkich w trzy sekundy.
You have friends in my class, do you not?
Masz w tej klasie przyjaciół, prawda?
Shinichi, are you home?
Shinichi, jesteś w domu?
Impressive.
Jestem pod wrażeniem.
I did not expect her to elicit such terror from you.
Nie sądziłem, że tak cię wystraszy.
That's cold!
Zimna! Dlaczego to robisz?
You took the bus yesterday evening, didn't you?
Jechałeś wczoraj autobusem, prawda?
Where did you go?
Dokąd?
Satomi was worried about you, too.
Satomi też się martwiła.
Oh, nowhere really.
To nieważne.
Shinichi, we are under attack.
Shinichi, atakują nas.
I sense nothing but killing intent from it.
Czuję, że chcą nas zabić.
-Huh? -Sensei?
- Co? - Sensei.
What's wrong?
Co się stało?
Fool.
Głupiec.
Someone, help!
Pomocy!
Hey, are you all right?
Nic panu nie jest?
We have an intruder.
Mamy tu intruza.
Call the police!
Wezwijcie policję!
Evacuate the students!
Ewakuować uczniów!
You will now study on your own.
Uczcie się sami.
We're under attack? From who?
Kto nas atakuje?
Most likely the male we met yesterday.
Facet, którego wczoraj poznaliśmy.
Hold it!
Stój!
Why did you enter the school grounds without permission?
Dlaczego wtargnąłeś na teren szkoły?
Come with me!
Pójdziesz ze mną!
He just neutralized three obstacles.
Usunął trzy przeszkody.
You mean he killed people?
Zabił ludzi?
I am not sure,
Nie wiem na pewno,
but he is certainly brash.
ale jest brutalny.
A knife?
Nóż?
Dear God! The intruder has a knife?
Dobry Boże! Intruz ma nóż?
This is an emergency announcement!
Uwaga, alarm!
There is an intruder in the building!
W budynku jest intruz!
-Huh? -Students are to follow
Co? Intruz?
-Evacuate? -and evacuate to the school grounds.
Ewakuacja?
I don't remember them saying there'd be a safety drill today.
Nic nie mówili o ćwiczeniach.
…in groups according to class.
Powtarzam. W budynku jest intruz.
Dammit! I can't believe he's doing this in broad daylight!
Cholera! Robi to w środku dnia?
He's optimistic about his chances and lacks forethought.
Myśli, że wygra, i brak mu przezorności.
-…and evacuate to the school grounds. -He's not at all like Tamiya Ryoko.
Nie jest jak Tamiya Ryoko.
Hey, where is she, anyway?
A gdzie ona jest?
She is approximately 150 meters away.
Jest 150 metrów stąd.
It appears she intends to observe our fight.
Będzie obserwować naszą walkę.
Guess that's better than her joining the enemy.
Dobrze, że do niego nie dołączy.
Evacuate using the stairs near Wing C
Wyjdźcie schodami w skrzydle C.
and do not approach Wing A under any circumstances.
Nie zbliżajcie się do skrzydła A!
Tamiya-sensei!
Tamiya-sensei!
She's not here?
Nie ma jej tu?
All right, come with me.
Chodźcie ze mną.
Don't push!
Nie pchać się!
Don't push. Stay in line and keep moving.
Ustawcie się i idźcie do przodu.
We should fight, Shinichi.
Musimy walczyć, Shinichi.
Fight? Why?
Walczyć? Dlaczego?
Our opponent strode in without any regard for witnesses in broad daylight.
Nasz przeciwnik wtargnął tutaj w środku dnia, nie bacząc na świadków.
Even if we run, he will come after us.
Będzie nas ścigał.
It's better to take him out now.
Lepiej z nim walczyć.
But…
Ale…
Besides, we currently have the advantage.
Poza tym teraz mamy przewagę.
I have a plan.
Mam plan.
A plan?
Plan?
Hey, who have you been talking to?
Z kim rozmawiasz?
Huh? Oh, just thinking out loud.
Co? Tylko głośno myślę.
Hey, think that's the intruder?
To ten intruz?
Huh? Where?
Co? Gdzie?
Over there. That middle-aged dude.
Ten koleś w średnim wieku.
No way!
Nie wierzę!
There really is an intruder!
To naprawdę intruz!
Hey, stay in line!
Ustawcie się!
He is attempting to pinpoint your, no, my location,
Próbuje cię zlokalizować, to znaczy mnie,
but this crowd is preventing him.
ale tłum mu w tym przeszkadza.
If…
Co będzie, jeśli nas znajdzie?
He will attack us, of course,
To jasne, że nas zaatakuje.
along with everyone around us. He will not hold back.
I wszystkich wokół nas. Nie będzie się hamował.
But that is also what we want.
Ale tego właśnie chcemy.
What we want?
Czego?
As he scythes down the people around you,
Gdy będzie zabijał osoby wokół nas,
I will move swiftly to pierce his heart.
szybko przebiję mu serce.
It's simplistic,
To prosty plan,
but it has a high probability of success.
ale może się udać.
The people around me?
Ludzi wokół nas?
That's your…
Taki masz…
Yes, that's my plan.
Tak, taki mam plan.
You are being protected by a shield, a "wall of meat", you could say.
Można powiedzieć, że chroni cię „ściana z mięsa”.
To A, it should pose a most inconvenient obstacle.
Dla X to będzie najgorsza przeszkoda.
A "wall of meat".
„Ściana z mięsa”.
I had forgotten what you are!
Zapomniałem, czym jesteś!
-Murano! -Izumi-kun!
- Murano! - Izumi-kun!
Did you forget something?
Zapomniałeś czegoś? Pójdę z tobą!
Don't come near me! Get away from me!
Nie zbliżaj się do mnie!
What?
Co?
Oh… Sorry!
Przepraszam!
Just get out of here and take refuge fast!
Uciekaj stąd i się ukryj!
What's the matter, Shinichi?
Co jest, Shinichi?
You did not find my plan to your liking?
Mój plan ci się nie podobał?
Of course not!
Jasne, że nie!
How many people do you intend to kill?
Ile osób chciałeś zabić?
But it's to protect myself.
Muszę chronić siebie.
You sacrifice other lives so that your own life can continue.
Poświęcamy innych, żeby przetrwać.
That is how animals live.
Tak żyją zwierzęta.
Your Japanese is really good.
Dużo się nauczyłeś.
You understand human speech so well,
Świetnie rozumiesz ludzką mowę.
yet, why do you…
Więc dlaczego…
I remember now.
Już pamiętam.
Humans are one-of-a-kind creatures that commit suicide.
Tylko ludzie popełniają samobójstwo.
It's not that I want to die.
Nie robię tego, bo chcę umrzeć.
What are you doing?
Co robisz?
This is a better option than using a wall of meat.
To lepsze niż wykorzystanie ściany z mięsa.
Class 3-2!
Klasa 3-2!
Stay in line!
Pilnujcie się!
Are you upset, Migi?
Jesteś zły, Migi?
Upset?
Zły?
I do not have time for that.
Nie mam na to czasu.
I must think of our next move.
Muszę przemyśleć nasz kolejny ruch.
Shinichi, what do you think separates us from A?
Shinichi, co różni nas od X?
What separates us?
Co nas różni?
He's a killer
On jest zabójcą,
and I'm a morally upright high school student.
a ja jestem uczniem z zasadami.
He can become someone else.
On może stać się kimś innym.
I can't.
Ja nie mogę.
He's one.
On jest jeden.
I am two.
- Nas jest dwóch. - Czyżby?
Does A perceive us as being two distinct entities?
Czy X uważa nas za dwie różne istoty?
What do you mean?
To znaczy?
Here's your weapon, Shinichi.
To twoja broń.
"My" weapon?
„Moja” broń?
That's right.
Tak.
A and I are just about evenly matched.
X i ja jesteśmy sobie równi.
So there is only one solution.
Więc jest jedno wyjście.
You must join in the fight.
Musisz dołączyć do walki.
If you become flustered and hold me back,
Jeśli się przestraszysz i mnie powstrzymasz,
we will lose.
przegramy.
On the other hand, if you fight effectively, we will win.
Ale jeśli będziesz skutecznie walczył, to wygramy.
"Effectively"? How?
„Skutecznie”? Jak?
We delegate roles.
Podzielimy się rolami.
See…
Słuchaj…
Will that really work?
To się uda?
Well, let's try it out.
Spróbujmy.
Conceal that weapon.
Schowaj tę broń.
It's true that Migi is far more of a combat expert than I am.
Migi lepiej zna się na walce niż ja.
He's already killed two of his kind.
Zabił już dwóch swoich.
Right. I just have to trust him.
Tak. Muszę mu zaufać.
He's coming, Shinichi.
Idzie.
A is within three meters of us.
Jest trzy metry od nas.
Three meters?
Trzy metry?
-I don't see him! -He's directly below us.
- Nie widzę go! - Jest pod nami.
Was that meant to be a barricade?
To ma być barykada?
You've only cut off your escape route.
Tylko odciąłeś sobie drogę ucieczki.
Next time, "Disheveled Hair."
Następny odcinek: „Rozczochrane włosy”.